

Alaric D'Souza

Resident Physican

714-926-4569

alaricdsouza.github.io

id orcid: 0000-0002-8744-8136

alaric.dsouza@childrens.harvard.edu

About me ——

Alaric is a Resident Pediatrician in the Boston Combined Residency Program, and he cares for pediatric patients at Boston Children's Hospital and Boston Medical Center. He did his MD/PhD at Washington University in St. Louis, and his Computational and Systems Biology dissertation research on Microbial Ecology and antibiotic resistance genes in the Dantas Lab. Alaric is applying for Pediatric Infectious Diseases Fellowships, and he hopes lead his own research group studying microbial communities and host-pathogen interactions.

Skills ——

Software Packages Adobe Illustrator, Adobe Photoshop, EndNote, LaTeX, Microsoft Office

Programming Languages Python, R, Bash, Wolfram Mathematica

Languages English (native) Hindi (beginner)

Misc

Computer Hardware, Machining and Fabrication, Welding

research interests

Microbial ecology, bacterial genomics, and antibiotic resistance.

education

2014-22 MD Washington University in St. Louis

2016-20 PhD Dantas Lab, Washington University in St. Louis Computational and Systems Biology

2010-14 BS Yale University Ecology and Evolutionary Biology

research and work experience

2022-pres. Pediatrics Residency

Resident Physician | Medical care for pediatric patients at Boston Children's Hospital, Brigham and Women's Hospital, and Boston Medical Center.

2016-20 Dantas Lab Washington University in St. Louis Doctoral Candidate | Ecology of hospital built environment bacteria, international travelers, and infant gut microbiota.

2015 Dantas Lab Washington University in St. Louis Rotation Student | Autologous Fecal Microbial Transplant Analysis

2012-14 Powell Lab Yale University
Undergraduate Researcher | Foraging behavior of Aedes aegypti
mosquitoes.

2013 Gagneux Lab Swiss Tropical and Public Health Institute Undergraduate Researcher | Antibiotic resistance and mutation rates in *Mycobacterium tuberculosis*.

2012 Schlesinger Lab The Ohio State University Undergraduate Researcher | Macrophage receptor signaling for *My-cobacterium tuberculosis* phagosome lysosome fusion escape.

2011 Seva Dhan Mumbai, India Summer Intern | Treatment of alcoholics and drug addicts.

2011 Course Consulting Canyon High School
Consultant | Course design for AP Psychology and IB Theory of Knowledge.

2009 Mentee of Dr. P.S. Wijewarnasuriya Army Research Labs Summer Intern | Semiconductor photoresist optimization for infrared detectors.

publications

* authors contributed equally

Acute and persistent effects of commonly-used antibiotics on the gut microbiome and resistome in healthy adults

Anthony WE, Wang B, Sukhum KV, D'Souza AW, Hink T, Cass C, Seiler S, Reske KA, Coon C, Dubberke ER, Burnham CA, Dantas G, Kwon JH *Cell Reports* | 10.1016/j.celrep.2022.110649

Structural and molecular rationale for the diversification of resistance mediated by the Antibiotic_NAT family
 Stogios PJ, Bordeleau E, Xu Z, Skarina T, Evdokimova E, Chou S, Diorio-Toth L, D'Souza AW, Patel S, Dantas G, Wright GD, Savchenko A

Communications Biology | 10.1038/s42003-022-03219-w

Destination shapes antibiotic resistance gene acquisitions, abundance increases, and diversity changes in Dutch travelers.
 D'Souza AW*, Boolchandani M*, Patel S, Galazzo G, Hattem J, Arcilla M, Melles D, Jong M, Schultsz C, Dantas G, Penders J

Genome Medicine | 10.1186/s13073-021-00893-z

2021	Manure microbial communities and resistance profiles reconfigure after transition to manure pits and differ from fertilized field soil
	Sukhum K, Vargas R, D'Souza AW, Boolchandani M, Patel S, Kesaraju A, Walljasper G, Hedge H, Ye Z, Valenzuela R, Gunderson P, Bendixsen C, Dantas G, Shukla S <i>mBio</i> 10.1128/mBio.00798-21
2020	Environmental remodeling of human gut microbiota and antibiotic resistome in livestock farms Sun J*, Liao XP*, D'Souza AW*, Boolchandani M*, Li SH*, Cheng K, Martinez JL, Li L, Feng YJ, Fang LX, Huang T, Xia J, Yu Y, Zhou YF, Sun YX, Deng XB, Zeng ZL, Jiang HX, Fang BH, Tang YZ, Lian XL, Zhang RM, Fang ZW, Yan QL, Dantas G, Liu YH Nature Communications 10.1038/s41467-020-15222-y
2019	Genomic characterization of antibiotic resistant <i>Escherichia coli</i> isolated from domestic chickens in Pakistan Rafique M*, Potter RF*, Ferreiro A, Wallace MA, Rahim A, Malik AA, Siddique N, Abbas MA, D'Souza AW, Burnham CD, Ali N, Dantas G <i>Frontiers in Microbiology</i> 10.3389/fmicb.2019.03052
2019	Cotrimoxazole prophylaxis increases resistance gene prevalence and α -diversity but decreases β -diversity in the gut microbiome of HIV-exposed, uninfected infants. D'Souza AW*, Moodley-Govender E*, Berla B, Kelkar T, Wang B, Sun X, Daniels B, Coutsoudis A, Trehan I, Dantas G Clinical Infectious Diseases 10.1093/cid/ciz1186
2019	Breakpoint beware: reliance on historical breakpoints for Enterobacteriaceae leads to discrepancies in interpretation of susceptibility testing for carbapenems and cephalosporins and gaps in detection of carbapenem-resistant organisms. Yarbrough ML, Wallace MA, Potter RF, D'Souza AW, Dantas G, Burnham CD European Journal of Clinical Microbiology & Infectious Diseases 10.1007/s10096-019-03711-y
2019	Spatiotemporal dynamics of multidrug resistant bacteria on intensive care unit surfaces. D'Souza AW*, Potter RF*, Wallace M, Shupe A, Patel S, Sun X, Gul D, Kwon JH, Andleeb S, Burnham CD, Dantas G Nature Communications 10.1038/s41467-019-12563-1
2019	Phenotypic and genotypic characterization of linezolid resistant <i>Enterococcus faecium</i> from the USA and Pakistan. Wardenburg K*, Potter R*, D'Souza AW, Hussain T, Wallace M, Andleeb A, Burnham CA, Dantas G <i>Journal of Antimicrobial Chemotherapy</i> 10.1093/jac/dkz367
2019	Sequencing-based methods and resources to study antimicrobial resistance. Boolchandani M*, D'Souza AW*, Dantas G Nature Reviews Genetics 10.1038/s41576-019-0108-4
2018	Infant diet and maternal gestational weight gain predict early metabolic maturation of gut microbiomes. Baumann-Dudenhoeffer AM, D'Souza AW, Tarr PI, Warner BB, Dantas G Nature Medicine 10.1038/s41591-018-0216-2
2018	Superficieibacter electus gen. nov., sp. nov., an Extended-Spectrum β -Lactamase Possessing Member of the Enterobacteriaceae Family, Isolated From Intensive Care Unit Surfaces. Potter RF*, D'Souza AW*, Wallace MA, Shupe A, Patel S, Gul D, Kwon JH, Beatty W, Andleeb S, Burnham CD, Dantas G Frontiers in Microbiology 10.3389/fmicb.2018.01629
2017	Draft Genome Sequence of the <i>bla</i> OXA-436- and <i>bla</i> NDM-1-Harboring <i>Shewanella putrefaciens</i> SA70 Isolate. Potter RF*, D'Souza AW*, Wallace MA, Shupe A, Patel S, Gul D, Kwon JH, Andleeb S, Burnham CD, Dantas G <i>Genome Announcements</i> 10.1128/genomeA.00644-17
2016	The rapid spread of carbapenem-resistant Enterobacteriaceae. Potter RF*, D'Souza AW*, Dantas G Drug Resistance Updates 10.1016/j.drup.2016.09.002
2014	Malignant cancer and invasive placentation: A case for positive pleiotropy between endometrial and malignancy phenotypes. D'Souza AW and Wagner GP Evolution, Medicine, and Public Health 10.1093/emph/eou022

published	labstracts
2021	Microbiome and immune disruption accompany mouse death in a gnotobiotic mouse model of neonatal sepsis Schwartz D, Wardenburg K, Shalon N, Ning J, Crofts T, D?Souza A, Robinson J, Henderson J, Warner B, Tarr P, Dantas G Journal of the Pediatric Infectious Diseases Society 10.1093/jpids/piab031.010
2020	The Gut Microbiome and Resistome of Healthy Volunteers are Restructured After Short Courses of Antibiotics Anthony W, Sukhum K, Cass C, Reske K, Seiler S, Hink T, Coon C, D'Souza A, Wang B, Sun S, Dubberke E, Burnham C-A, Dantas G, Kwon JH Infection Control & Hospital Epidemiology 10.1017/ice.2020.476
2017	Longitudinal Analysis of ICU Surface Multidrug-resistant Organism Contamination in the US and Pakistan Kwon JH, D'Souza A, Potter R, Wallace M, Shupe A, Patel S, Gul D, Andleeb S, Burnham C-A, Dantas G Open Forum Infectious Diseases 10.1093/ofid/ofx163.245
2015	Autologous Fecal Microbiota Transplantation as a Strategy to Prevent Colonization With Multidrug-Resistant Organisms Following Antimicrobial Therapy Bulow C, D'Souza A, Hink T, Wallace M, Reske K, Sun X, Kwon JH, Burnham C-A, Dantas G, Dubberke E Open Forum Infectious Diseases 10.1093/ofid/ofv133.479
invited tal	lks
2022	Impacts of swine farm exposure on the human gut microbiota and resistome though genomics and metage- nomics Leman Swine Conference
2021	6 mo M presenting with 5 days of fever, emesis, and irritability BJC/SLCH Infectious Diseases Grand Rounds
2021	An exploration of Emergency Department turnaround time data WUSTL Clinical Informatics Seminar
2021	Total thyroidectomy in a 15 yo F with familial adenomatous polyposis WUSTL GI Seminar
2021	Angiomyolipoma in a 9 yo F with tuberous sclerosis WUSTL Pathology Seminar
2020	16S rRNA gene sequencing in bacterial endocarditis WUSTL Lab Medicine Seminar
2019	Effects of antibiotic prophylaxis on the HIV-exposed uninfected infant gut microbiome WUSTL MSTP Work in Progress Seminar
2018	Bacterial contamination on hospital ICU surfaces in the United States and Pakistan WUSTL Microbiology Department Seminar
2018	Bacterial contamination on hospital ICU surfaces in the United States and Pakistan WUSTL Center for Genome Sciences

2018 Bacterial contamination on hospital ICU surfaces in the United States and Pakistan

American Society of Microbiology Micro

Bacterial contamination on hospital ICU surfaces in the United States and Pakistan 2017

CSB-MMMP-PMB Interdepartmental Retreat

2017 Multidrug resistant organisms on hospital surfaces in the United States and Pakistan

Computational and Systems Biology Retreat

2017 Longitudinal analysis of ICU surface microbial contamination in the United States and Pakistan

American Society of Microbiology Micro

2017 Effects of trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole on the microbiomes of HIV- infants born to HIV+ mothers

WUSTL Center for Genome Sciences

Antibiotic Resistance: a growing public health crisis 2017

WUSTL Institute of Public Health

2013 Drop Team and Rayleigh-Taylor instability

Canyon High School AP biology class

2012 Mannose Receptor Signaling

SUCCESS

patents

2018 Store-Easy Automotive wheelchair storage device.

Patent US9937088B2

Guertler C, D'Souza AW, Milgrom R, Hong T, Xiao Y, Nadell S

posters

2019	Spatiotemporal dynamics of multidrug resistant bacteria on intensive care unit surfaces.
	Than A Autorio A 41 1 14/Th

IMM/MICRO Mini WIP

2019 Cotrimoxazole prophylaxis increases resistance gene prevalence and α -diversity but decreases β -diversity

in the gut microbiome of HIV-exposed, uninfected infants.

American Society of Microbiology (ASM) Microbe

2019 Longitudinal analysis of ICU surface microbial contamination in the US and Pakistan

NIAID/IDSA Infectious Diseases Research Careers Meeting

2018 Longitudinal Analysis of ICU Surface Microbial Contamination in the US and Pakistan

American Physician Scientist Association (APSA) Midwest meeting

2018 Longitudinal Analysis of ICU Surface Microbial Contamination in the US and Pakistan

Lake Arrowhead Microbial Genomics Conference

2018 Longitudinal Analysis of ICU Surface Microbial Contamination in the US and Pakistan

American Society of Microbiology (ASM) Microbe

2017 Longitudinal Analysis of ICU Surface Microbial Contamination in the US and Pakistan

American Society of Microbiology (ASM) Microbe

2017 Longitudinal Analysis of ICU Surface Microbial Contamination in the US and Pakistan

5th annual Global Health & Infectious Disease Conference

2014 Invasive populations of Aedes aegypti in Central California

Yale Ecology and Evolutionary Biology Poster Session

The genetics of foraging behavior in *Aedes aegypti*

Cell Symposia: Genes, Circuits, and Behavior

2012 Mannose receptor signaling linking spleen tyrosine kinase and MAP kinase p38 in human macrophages

The Ohio State University SUCCESS program

2009 Relationship of spinning time and speed to photoresist thickness on semiconductor wafers

Army Research Labs: Science and Engineering Apprentice Program

[awards]

2022	F. Sessions Cole Award in Pediati	rics

2022 Alexander Berg Prize

2022 Washington University Internal Medicine Club Research Award

2021 Gold Humanism Honor Society Inductee

2020 Spencer T. and Ann W. Olin Fellow

2017-18 Burroughs Wellcome Fund, Institutional Program Unifying Population and Laboratory-Based Sciences

2016 BioEnterpreneurship Core Bench to Business Competition

2015 IDEA Labs Demo Day Finalist

2013 Alan S. Tetelman Fellowship for International Research in the Sciences

2013 Paul K. and Evelyn Elizabeth Cook Richter Fellowship

2013 Connecticut Space Grant College Consortium Student Project Grant

2012 CBC Spouses Cheerios Brand Health Initiative Scholarship

2011 CBC Louis Stokes Health Scholarship2010 CBC Louis Stokes Health Scholarship

professional memberships

2022-pres.	American Academy of Pediatrics
2021-pres.	Gold Humanism Honor Society

2019-pres. Infectious Diseases Society of America2016-pres. American Society for Microbiology

teaching

2022-pres. 2017-20	Clinical instruction of medical students from Harvard, Boston University, and Tufts Medical Schools Computational Teaching Assistant Fundamentals of Biostatistics Washington University in St. Louis
2017-20	Graduate Mentor Visiting scholars, rotation students, and undergraduates Dantas Lab
2017	Teaching Assistant Microbes and Pathogenesis Washington University in St. Louis
2017	Graduate Mentor IPH Summer Program Washington University in St. Louis
2016	Graduate Mentor Eureka Program Washington University in St. Louis
2013-14	Lecturer Origins of Life Yale Splash
2011-14	Lecturer The Science of Ice Cream Yale Splash

activities and leadership

activities c	interior reader 5 mp
2022-pres.	Reviewer Independent peer review of manuscripts on bacterial genomics and metagenomics
2021-pres.	Reviewer Independent peer review of manuscripts on bacterial genomics and metagenomics
2020	Volunteer Maker Task Force, Washington University in St. Louis/Barnes Jewish Hospital Helped produce face shields for hospital
2019-2020	Volunteer Saturday Neighborhood Health Clinic Seeing patients as a medical student volunteer for the free clinic
2014-pres.	Yale Admissions Interviewer Interviewer for Yale College admissions of prospective undergraduate students Yale Alumni Schools Committee
2015-17	Physicians for Human Rights Co-President of club focusing on human rights and political issues that relate to medicine, including health-care for prisoner, refugees, and underserved communities
2014-17	Store-Easy Washington University in St. Louis - Sling Health Company seeking to improve manual wheelchair storage in automobiles
2012-14	NASA Microgravity University (Drop Team) Vale University Undergraduate research team selected by NASA to conduct fluid mechanics research in zero-gravity
2012-14	Splash at Yale University Undergraduate group teaching short courses to middle and high school students
2011-14	Big Sib Mentor to freshman students at Yale University Yale University - Pierson College